<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Learning on James&#39; Blog</title>
    <link>https://hkwind.github.io/categories/learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Learning on James&#39; Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2008–2018, Steve Francia and the Hugo Authors; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hkwind.github.io/categories/learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Learning how to learn - A Cousera course Introduction</title>
      <link>https://hkwind.github.io/post/learning-how-to-learn/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hkwind.github.io/post/learning-how-to-learn/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;“Learning how to learn” is one of the most popular courses on Coursera. Check out this summary blog article and later if you are interested, go try out the completely free course!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!---thumbnail = &#34;&#34;--&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
#	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/MillionareInYou_CoverPic.jpg&#34; width = &#34;200&#34;/&gt;
# &lt;/p&gt;--&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;foreword&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreword&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome! Great to see you here!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Learning how to learn&amp;quot; is a 4-week course introducing different topics about effective learning each week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I will not go through everything about the course, as I believe you should attend it to understand how to learn effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I will only introduce the inspiring concepts and ideas from this course that I have applied in studying other topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope these techniques can help you in your learning journey as well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Course link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&#34;&gt;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tackling-procrastination拖延how-to-start-learning&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tackling Procrastination（拖延）(How to start learning)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Procrastination is my biggest enemy. I must admit that I tend to avoid doing tedious work and move on to an activity that brings me pleasure. However, I often regret spending meaningless hours doing nothing, which leads to no actual accomplishments. Worse, the guilt may lead to a vicious circle, forcing me to do more leisure activities to escape from these negative feelings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course has mentioned several ideas to tackle procrastination. Some of them work for me effectively. Before mentioning them, I must point out that using willpower to defeat the idea of delaying is not a good measure. Some practices can help us to conquer it. Special shoutout to Pomodoro. It&#39;s a practical supporting tool and mindset that enhances study effectiveness. A dedicated section below introduces it and other tools useful for learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;planning&#34;&gt;Planning&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, make a plan. In the course, the instructor suggests everyone should maintain a planner journal and plan their next day before bed. By doing so, we remind ourselves of close deadlines and avoid rushing through everything (thus better products!). Also, it is suggested to plan the most crucial and disliked task as the first task in the morning. We should be rested and back in the groove when we wake up. Therefore, we can use our 100% energy to focus on the task. After accomplishing it, we will have a sense of accomplishment throughout the day, leading to extra motivation towards the remaining hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally use a goal tracker to monitor my deadlines. Feel free to check my template out and use it to your own benefit.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1p54_NT58cR-NeDzRlMl5Ar9J3nxv2sBLot3eB8j6STw/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1p54_NT58cR-NeDzRlMl5Ar9J3nxv2sBLot3eB8j6STw/edit?usp=sharing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;focus-on-the-process&#34;&gt;Focus on the Process&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is to focus on the process rather than the product. Products can be scary, for example, a 5000-word essay, a project that weighs 50% of your total grade, or even blog articles that require updating weekly. We may want to escape from these intimidating aims, resulting in procrastination. Instead, focus on the process: &amp;quot;Writing for an hour&amp;quot;. Does not seem that scary now. As long as we are productive and working on the right path, the outcome matters but is not the sole focus anymore. We may be surprised at how productive we can be by several hours!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;remove-procrastination-cues&#34;&gt;Remove Procrastination Cues&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third is to put yourself in surroundings with few procrastination cues. Most of us are weak and easily attracted to many things: mobile phones, TV, computers, people… As soon as these things catch our attention, we lose focus on our current task or even stop doing it. To avoid it from happening, find a place with the least attractions, for example, a study room. Especially for your phones, place them somewhere you cannot see them. You can do whatever you want with your phone during rest periods, but do your best to focus on tasks when working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-learn-better&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Learn Better&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course introduces several concepts to learn effectively. What I found the most noteworthy is the idea of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;Illusion of Competence&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  It means that our actions lead to a false sense that we have already understood the concepts. For example, we may just glance through the answer to a question and feel like we have a grasp of the way to answer similar questions. Another common loophole is that we highlight and underline the key concepts and all of a sudden fully understand what it means. We may even just practice on the easy stuff and truly believe that we have mastered the skill! These are just illusions, which will break when we face real difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the course has introduced concepts and techniques that help us to 1. memorize and 2. become proficient in different fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;spaced-repetition-technique&#34;&gt;Spaced Repetition Technique&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, we think we have memorized something, but after a few hours or days, we forget them. It is because we only remember them in our working memory, but not in long-term memory. To access long term memory and really remember something, the “Spaced Repetition Technique” is the way to go. Instead of forcing yourself to learn something in an hour and never revise it again, try to do shorter intervals but in several days. By recalling after some time, it helps to form and strengthen our long term memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;metaphor-and-analogy&#34;&gt;Metaphor and Analogy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do have to understand things before we can memorize them. Also, memorizing a cumbersome chunk of concepts without paraphrasing is hard. We can try using Metaphor and Analogy to paraphrase ideas into things that are easier to remember. By drawing an imaginary picture in our head, we can access our visual memory system. It gives us an extra cue to remember stuff and effectively stores them in our long-term memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;diffuse-mode&#34;&gt;Diffuse Mode&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course mentioned techniques on how to tackle problems as well. Solving problems show our competence to utilize the knowledge in our brain and ensure that we have fully understood the concepts. The instructor suggests that &amp;quot;Diffuse mode&amp;quot; is crucial when conquering problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our brains have a focused mode and a diffuse mode. The focused mode works when we are concentrating on tasks, while the diffuse mode works when we are not. Studies show that we are more creative and good at solving challenging questions when in diffuse mode. Therefore, next time you are struggling with a question or task, try to do easier questions or be relaxed to activate diffuse mode!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;suggested-tools&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suggested tools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;pomodoro&#34;&gt;Pomodoro&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pomodoro is actually a very well known technique. I knew about it even before attending the course. However, I have seen many failed cases online, claiming that Pomodoro has no help in their study or work. I believe that how to utilize Pomodoro is more important than the technique itself. A book review related to Pomodoro (in Chinese only) will be posted in the coming weeks. Stay tuned if you want to know more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pomodoro has two significant rules to follow in my opinion. The first is allowing resting periods between working sections. As most of you may know, Pomodoro consists of a cycle of working sections that lasts for around 25-30 mins then followed by a 5-10 mins rest. After 4 or more working sections, you can rest for a longer period (10-30 min). Most people understand this logic but neglect the importance of the rest period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can only be fully focused for a period of time, then our productivity will go lower and lower as time passes. By resting (i.e. not doing work-related stuff and relaxing), first we can recharge our energy and be better prepared in the next working section. What&#39;s more, it enables diffuse mode (mentioned above) thus it helps us to solve complicated problems as well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is to be focused on one and only one task when in one working section. If you have ideas and thoughts related to other topics during working, use a notebook to mark them down. It is to ensure that we can dedicate most of our attention and energy to our work in front of us. Email checking, Instagram checking, booking a concert ticket... Sure, but do it in resting periods or next Pomodoro period. Focus on one task at a time shows better results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ending&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ending&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course has also mentioned the Anki flashcard system, which is a tool for memorizing things. I will try it in my later study and may add an additional paragraph introducing it later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, hope you enjoyed reading this article and learn a thing or two. Feel free to check out my other blog post and also the course!
Course link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&#34;&gt;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
