<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Programming on James&#39; Blog</title>
    <link>https://hkwind.github.io/categories/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Programming on James&#39; Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2008–2018, Steve Francia and the Hugo Authors; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hkwind.github.io/categories/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s build a blog with GitHub and Hugo - Part 1 - GitHub Settings</title>
      <link>https://hkwind.github.io/post/howtobuildablog_part1_github/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hkwind.github.io/post/howtobuildablog_part1_github/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Wanna blog? Follow the instruction and build yourself a blog in a day or two!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!---thumbnail = &#34;&#34;--&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
#	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/MillionareInYou_CoverPic.jpg&#34; width = &#34;200&#34;/&gt;
# &lt;/p&gt;--&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: &lt;br /&gt; I’m not an expert in building a blog and I do not know every feature in Github &amp;amp; Hugo. &lt;br /&gt;
However, we are on the same learning journey. I would love to share what I have learnt. &lt;br /&gt;
Therefore, if you have some problems, feel free to raise them. Then, we can discuss it here and everyone can learn something from it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;foreword&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreword&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome! I suppose you want to start blogging. For whatever purpose, that does not matter.
What matters is that you do want to build your own blog, and you stumble upon this article.
In this series of blog articles, I’ll show you how to create your own website and blog, and more importantly how to maintain it. Let&#39;s get started!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub is a place where developers can upload, manage and control versions of their code. In technical terms, it is called a repository.
What’s unique about Github is that it can be used as a hosting service provider.
Therefore, after we upload our code and do some settings changes in GitHub, it will automatically help us build a website! How convenient!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;create-github-account&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create GitHub Account&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step is to create a GitHub account. First, go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/&#34;&gt;https://github.com/&lt;/a&gt; and start the signup procedure. GitHub gives clear instructions, so you can simply follow them. One thing to notice: Be careful about your username, as it should be shown in your website URL later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_CreateUser.png&#34; width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_SelectFeature.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As before mentioned, we will be going with the costless option i.e. the free plan.
The GitHub free plan has already got all the functionalities we need.
If you are feeling good later and wants to upgrade, it&#39;s up to you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_Free_Plan.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;create-project-repository&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create Project Repository&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After filling in all required information and finishing all necessary verifications, you should be led to the dashboard page.
This is the so-called front page, and you can access all of your projects here.
Click the &amp;quot;New&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Create repository&amp;quot; button on the left panel to start building your account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_CreateRepository.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For repository name, it should be &amp;quot;yourusername&amp;quot;.github.io.
For example, as my username is &amp;quot;testinguser0122&amp;quot;, my repository name should be ‘testinguser0122.github.io‘.
This is also the URL people use to access your blog.
Beware that the repository should be public as GitHub web hosting services are only free for public repositories.
As for the below option, we should add a readme file (for introduction purposes) and add a license (GNU General Public License v3.0).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_CreateRepositoryFillData.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all settings have been set, we can click “Create” and the repository is ready!
As you can see, our repository only have two files: A README file and the LICENSE file.
We should add more files to it, but for now we can leave it as be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_RepositoryFrontPage.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;create-our-own-website&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create our own Website&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After setting up the repository, its time to build our own website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to settings page which the button should be around the top right corner of the project page.
In settings, go to the Pages and select Docs branch as the source for the repository. Click “Save” and the confirmation message &amp;quot;Your website is published&amp;quot; is shown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_PageSettings.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can then see that the page is published and the website can be accessed now! Your website should almost look identical just like mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_Webpage.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ending&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ending&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are all set! Our website is built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well it looks blank and we have not yet put our content in.
&lt;br&gt;But don&#39;t worry, in the next blog, I will introduce you how to start making your blog. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s build a blog with GitHub and Hugo - Introduction</title>
      <link>https://hkwind.github.io/post/howtobuildablog_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hkwind.github.io/post/howtobuildablog_intro/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Wanna blog? Follow the instruction and build yourself a blog in a day or two!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!---thumbnail = &#34;&#34;--&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
#	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/MillionareInYou_CoverPic.jpg&#34; width = &#34;200&#34;/&gt;
# &lt;/p&gt;--&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: &lt;br /&gt; I’m not an expert in building a blog and I do not know every feature in Github &amp;amp; Hugo. &lt;br /&gt;
However, we are on the same learning journey. I would love to share what I have learnt. &lt;br /&gt;
Therefore, if you have some problems, feel free to raise them. Then, we can discuss it here and everyone can learn something from it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;foreword&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreword&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome! I suppose you want to start blogging. For whatever purpose, that does not matter.
What matters is that you do want to build your own blog, and you stumble upon this article.
In this series of blog articles, I’ll show you how to create your own website and blog, and more importantly how to maintain it. Let&#39;s get started!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this series, as the header says, we are using Github and Hugo to build the blog.
I’ve tried several ways to construct my blog, and eventually, I’m satisfied with this outcome.
That’s why at the start of this introduction article, I’m going to show you why I would build my blog with Github and Hugo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;advantages-of-using-github--hugo-to-build-a-blog&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantages of using GitHub &amp;amp; Hugo to build a blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;free-price&#34;&gt;Free Price&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, it is free. TOTALLY FREE. Not even a single penny was spent when building this blog. All you need is a PC to save the files, an internet connection so you can connect with the GitHub server, and an email (Google Mail is fine) account to create a Github account. Therefore, even if you are uncertain about whether you will continue blogging, your desire to try blogging won’t be deterred by the monthly / yearly subscription fee of those blog hosting sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;low-setup-difficulty&#34;&gt;Low Setup Difficulty&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, it is easy to set up. Of course, Medium and other blog hosting websites do not require setup at all, but free things come with a cost. However, the setup process of Github and Hugo are much less complicated than other free options, which makes this combination a better choice than the others. Usually, you can finish setup and post your first blog within the first few days if you have followed the steps in this blog carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;no-requirement-on-programming-knowledge&#34;&gt;No requirement on programming knowledge&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, you can build your own blog without any prerequisite programming knowledge. Or let me paraphrase it, you do not need any programming knowledge because I have done most of the programming work for you. What you need to do is follow the steps. However, you still have to know something about coding for uploading blogs (very easy) and customizing the blog (a bit harder), which will be discussed in later sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ending&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ending&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that has been said, I’m sure you understand what’s the benefit of going for the Github + Hugo approach. If you’re confident that you want to try it out, let&#39;s continue on our next blog: Create a GitHub account and domain.&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
