<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on James&#39; Blog</title>
    <link>https://hkwind.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on James&#39; Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2008–2018, Steve Francia and the Hugo Authors; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hkwind.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Learning how to learn - A Cousera course Introduction</title>
      <link>https://hkwind.github.io/post/learning-how-to-learn/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hkwind.github.io/post/learning-how-to-learn/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;“Learning how to learn” is one of the most popular courses on Coursera. Check out this summary blog article and later if you are interested, go try out the completely free course!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Learning How to Learn.png&#34; width = &#34;500&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;foreword&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreword&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome! Great to see you here!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Learning how to learn&amp;quot; is a 4-week course introducing different topics about effective learning each week.
&lt;br&gt;(Course link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&#34;&gt;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I will not go through everything about the course, as I believe you should attend it to understand how to learn effectively.
Therefore, I will only introduce the inspiring concepts and ideas from this course that I have applied in studying other topics.
Hope these techniques can help you in your learning journey as well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tackling-procrastination拖延how-to-start-learning&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tackling Procrastination（拖延）(How to start learning)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Procrastination is my biggest enemy. I must admit that I tend to avoid doing tedious work and move on to an activity that brings me pleasure. However, I often regret spending meaningless hours doing nothing, which leads to no actual accomplishments. Worse, the guilt may lead to a vicious circle, forcing me to do more leisure activities to escape from these negative feelings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course has mentioned several ideas to tackle procrastination. Some of them work for me effectively. Before mentioning them, I must point out that &lt;strong&gt;using willpower to defeat the idea of delaying&lt;/strong&gt; is not a good measure. Special shoutout to Pomodoro. It&#39;s a practical supporting tool and mindset that enhances study effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;planning&#34;&gt;Planning&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, make a plan. In the course, the instructor suggests everyone should maintain a planner journal and plan their next day before bed. By doing so, we remind ourselves of close deadlines and avoid rushing through everything (thus better products!). Also, it is suggested to plan the &lt;em&gt;most crucial and disliked task&lt;/em&gt; as the first task in the morning. We should be rested and back in the groove when we wake up. Therefore, we can use our 100% energy to focus on the task. After accomplishing it, we will have a sense of accomplishment throughout the day, leading to extra motivation towards the remaining hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally use a goal tracker to monitor my deadlines. Feel free to check my template out and use it to your own benefit.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1p54_NT58cR-NeDzRlMl5Ar9J3nxv2sBLot3eB8j6STw/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1p54_NT58cR-NeDzRlMl5Ar9J3nxv2sBLot3eB8j6STw/edit?usp=sharing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;focus-on-the-process&#34;&gt;Focus on the Process&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is to focus on the process rather than the product. Products can be scary, for example, a 5000-word essay, a project that weighs 50% of your total grade, or even blog articles that require updating weekly. We may want to escape from these intimidating aims, resulting in procrastination. Instead, focus on the process: &amp;quot;Writing for an hour&amp;quot;. Does not seem that scary now. As long as we are productive and working on the right path, the outcome matters but is not the sole focus anymore. We may be surprised at how productive we can be by several hours!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;remove-procrastination-cues&#34;&gt;Remove Procrastination Cues&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third is to put yourself in surroundings with few procrastination cues. Most of us are weak and easily attracted to many things: mobile phones, TV, computers, people… As soon as these things catch our attention, we lose focus on our current task or even stop doing it. To avoid it from happening, find a place with the least attractions, for example, a study room. Especially for your phones, place them somewhere you cannot see them. &lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can do whatever you want with your phone during rest periods, but do your best to focus on tasks when working.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-learn-better&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Learn Better&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course introduces several concepts to learn effectively. What I found the most noteworthy is the idea of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;Illusion of Competence&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  It means that our actions lead to a false sense that we have already understood the concepts. For example, we may just glance through the answer to a question and feel like we have a grasp of the way to answer similar questions. Another common loophole is that we highlight and underline the key concepts and all of a sudden fully understand what it means. We may even just practice on the easy stuff and truly believe that we have mastered the skill! These are just illusions, which will break when we face real difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the course has introduced concepts and techniques that help us to 1. memorize and 2. become proficient in different fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;spaced-repetition-technique&#34;&gt;Spaced Repetition Technique&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, we think we have memorized something, but after a few hours or days, we forget them. It is because we only remember them in our working memory, but not in long-term memory. To access long term memory and really remember something, the “Spaced Repetition Technique” is the way to go. Instead of forcing yourself to learn something in an hour and never revise it again, try to do shorter intervals but in several days. By recalling after some time, it helps to form and strengthen our long term memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;metaphor-and-analogy&#34;&gt;Metaphor and Analogy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do have to understand things before we can memorize them. Also, memorizing a cumbersome chunk of concepts without paraphrasing is hard. We can try using Metaphor and Analogy to paraphrase ideas into things that are easier to remember. By drawing an imaginary picture in our head, we can access our visual memory system. It gives us an extra cue to remember stuff and effectively stores them in our long-term memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;diffuse-mode&#34;&gt;Diffuse Mode&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course mentioned techniques on how to tackle problems as well. Solving problems show our competence to utilize the knowledge in our brain and ensure that we have fully understood the concepts. The instructor suggests that &amp;quot;Diffuse mode&amp;quot; is crucial when conquering problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our brains have a focused mode and a diffuse mode. The focused mode works when we are concentrating on tasks, while the diffuse mode works when we are not. Studies show that we are more creative and good at solving challenging questions when in diffuse mode. Therefore, next time you are struggling with a question or task, try to do easier questions or be relaxed to activate diffuse mode!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;suggested-tools&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suggested tools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;pomodoro&#34;&gt;Pomodoro&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pomodoro is actually a very well known technique. I knew about it even before attending the course. However, I have seen many failed cases online, claiming that Pomodoro has no help in their study or work. I believe that how to utilize Pomodoro is more important than the technique itself. A book review related to Pomodoro (in Chinese only) will be posted in the coming weeks. Stay tuned if you want to know more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pomodoro has two significant rules to follow in my opinion. The first is allowing resting periods between working sections. As most of you may know, Pomodoro consists of a cycle of working sections that lasts for around 25-30 mins then followed by a 5-10 mins rest. After 4 or more working sections, you can rest for a longer period (10-30 min). Most people understand this logic but neglect the importance of the rest period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/PomodoroTechnique.png&#34; width = &#34;500&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can only be fully focused for a period of time, then our productivity will go lower and lower as time passes. By resting (i.e. not doing work-related stuff and relaxing), first we can recharge our energy and be better prepared in the next working section. What&#39;s more, it enables diffuse mode (mentioned above) thus it helps us to solve complicated problems as well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is to be focused on one and only one task when in one working section. If you have ideas and thoughts related to other topics during working, use a notebook to mark them down. It is to ensure that we can dedicate most of our attention and energy to our work in front of us. Email checking, Instagram checking, booking a concert ticket... Sure, but do it in resting periods or next Pomodoro period. Focus on one task at a time shows better results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ending&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ending&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course has also mentioned the Anki flashcard system, which is a tool for memorizing things. I will try it in my later study and may add an additional paragraph introducing it later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, hope you enjoyed reading this article and learn a thing or two. Feel free to check out my other blog post and also the course!
Course link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&#34;&gt;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s build a blog with GitHub and Hugo - Introduction</title>
      <link>https://hkwind.github.io/post/howtobuildablog_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hkwind.github.io/post/howtobuildablog_intro/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Wanna blog? Follow the instruction and build yourself a blog in a day or two!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!---thumbnail = &#34;&#34;--&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
#	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/MillionareInYou_CoverPic.jpg&#34; width = &#34;200&#34;/&gt;
# &lt;/p&gt;--&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: &lt;br /&gt; I’m not an expert in building a blog and I do not know every feature in Github &amp;amp; Hugo. &lt;br /&gt;
However, we are on the same learning journey. I would love to share what I have learnt. &lt;br /&gt;
Therefore, if you have some problems, feel free to raise them. Then, we can discuss it here and everyone can learn something from it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;foreword&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreword&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome! I suppose you want to start blogging. For whatever purpose, that does not matter.
What matters is that you do want to build your own blog, and you stumble upon this article.
In this series of blog articles, I’ll show you how to create your own website and blog, and more importantly how to maintain it. Let&#39;s get started!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this series, as the header says, we are using Github and Hugo to build the blog.
I’ve tried several ways to construct my blog, and eventually, I’m satisfied with this outcome.
That’s why at the start of this introduction article, I’m going to show you why I would build my blog with Github and Hugo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;advantages-of-using-github--hugo-to-build-a-blog&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantages of using GitHub &amp;amp; Hugo to build a blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;free-price&#34;&gt;Free Price&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, it is free. TOTALLY FREE. Not even a single penny was spent when building this blog. All you need is a PC to save the files, an internet connection so you can connect with the GitHub server, and an email (Google Mail is fine) account to create a Github account. Therefore, even if you are uncertain about whether you will continue blogging, your desire to try blogging won’t be deterred by the monthly / yearly subscription fee of those blog hosting sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;low-setup-difficulty&#34;&gt;Low Setup Difficulty&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, it is easy to set up. Of course, Medium and other blog hosting websites do not require setup at all, but free things come with a cost. However, the setup process of Github and Hugo are much less complicated than other free options, which makes this combination a better choice than the others. Usually, you can finish setup and post your first blog within the first few days if you have followed the steps in this blog carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;no-requirement-on-programming-knowledge&#34;&gt;No requirement on programming knowledge&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, you can build your own blog without any prerequisite programming knowledge. Or let me paraphrase it, you do not need any programming knowledge because I have done most of the programming work for you. What you need to do is follow the steps. However, you still have to know something about coding for uploading blogs (very easy) and customizing the blog (a bit harder), which will be discussed in later sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ending&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ending&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that has been said, I’m sure you understand what’s the benefit of going for the Github + Hugo approach. If you’re confident that you want to try it out, let&#39;s continue on our next blog: Create a GitHub account and domain.&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>賺錢，也賺幸福</title>
      <link>https://hkwind.github.io/post/millionareinyou_20220101/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hkwind.github.io/post/millionareinyou_20220101/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;你有沒有想過，自己賺錢的目的是爲了甚麽？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;歡迎來到《賺錢，也賺幸福》的讀書會，讓我們一起來探討應該如何策劃自己的人生。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/MillionareInYou_CoverPic.jpg&#34; width = &#34;200&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Millionaire In You: Ten Things You Need To Do Now To Have Money And Time To Enjoy It&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;主動積極投資自己的人生，被動投資你的金錢
(麥可．勒巴夫 Michael LeBoeuf)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;前言&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;前言&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;你有沒有想過，自己工作的目的是爲了甚麽？每天辛勤工作，忙得連輕鬆的時間都欠奉，只爲了讓年老體衰時能過著不算太差的生活？除了工作，你又有沒有想過自己的人生還有著什麽目標？歡迎來到《賺錢，也賺幸福》的讀書會，讓我們一起來探討應該如何策劃自己的人生。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在此書内，作者一共列出了四大見解，十大選擇以及四大要務，個人覺得此書的每一個章節都有其獨特的見解，實在值得一看再看。但畢竟這是我個人的閲讀筆記，因此我並不會將其中的内容全部寫出，而是會對抽取其中的内容做一些整合以及加入一些個人心得。如果閱讀完這篇筆記后想瞭解更多内容，歡迎到各大書局或圖書館尋寶~&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;一規劃人生分配時間&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;一。規劃人生，分配時間&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;夢想&#34;&gt;夢想&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;你有想過未來一年，十年，二十年，甚至退休的時候，你希望自己正活著一個怎樣的人生嗎？如果沒有的話，不如現在就來想一下對於將來的盼望和目標？你可能會覺得夢想對你來説有一點不切實際。亦有可能，你會覺得夢想是不必要的，只需要專注於目前的工作就可以了。但是，「做人如果無夢想，同條鹹魚有咩分別呀？」夢想作爲我們的原動力，能夠推動我們成爲更好的自己。我們也需要夢想，引領我們走上一條我們享受的人生路。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果上面的問題對你來説有一點空泛，我們可以用書中的兩個問題作出發點：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;希望N年后的人生有些甚麽？&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;怎樣知道自己已經擁有了想要的東西？&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;第一個問題的答案當然可能會有非常多：很多很多錢，一個安身之所，甚至可以是開心這種比較虛無的概念（夢想應該是多方面的，包括個人成長，家庭及朋友，健康，等等），因此我們以第二個問題來令虛無的概念具體化，如「我擁有一百萬就等於很多很多錢」 / 「我一天能有三個小時的時間打機就等於開心」。一個具體化的夢想，有助我們去走下一步：訂立目標。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;目標&#34;&gt;目標&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;有了一個概念，或者説是對於未來的幻想之後，當然不可以止步於此。你需要做的，是將你的夢想化爲對於未來的規劃，並定下各種的目標，然後確實實行。
書中認爲目標應該具備可信性（是可以做到的事情），振奮性（達成時會令自己雀躍而非沮喪），明確性（一個可以量化的成果）以及完成期限（Deadline!!!)，例如「我在三年後銀行存款要有五十萬」。當你根據你的夢想訂立了不同的目標后，就將他們根據重要性排序，然後開始定出行動計劃。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;行動計劃&#34;&gt;行動計劃&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每一個目標都應該有它們各自的行動計劃，畢竟沒有行動的目標只是空想。跟目標一樣，行動計劃也是要具備另外，書中有一個概念叫做「即知即行」，意思是知道怎樣做就要開始去做。要知道每當我們給自己藉口拖延一天，我們離達成目標的日子就會遠一天。當然，我們也需要適當的休息，而且不斷的工作也只會令效率降低。因此，我們需要做的是計劃好后便坐言起行，一直追蹤自己的進度，並在適當的時候給予自己獎勵。
最後，要知道計劃一定不會完美無缺，意外終會發生，阻礙你順利完成計劃。在計劃中預留一些彈性的時間，可以令自己不會因爲意外而執行不了計劃，導致灰心喪志自暴自棄。
而且，有目標並堅定前進的人總會比懶散的人更容易獲得成功，宇宙會祝福你的~&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;二投資自己投資人生&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;二。投資自己，投資人生&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;其實跟規劃人生有一點類似，但這一部分會更加著重於投資。今年美國股市暢旺，加上加密貨幣、NFT 等新型的投資物品開始出現，相信每一個人都會想有開始投資的慾望或者已經開始進入了投資這個領域。不過呢，本書所宣導的投資方式卻與這些無緣。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;被動投資你的金錢&#34;&gt;被動投資你的金錢&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;這本書所宣導的投資方式，可以說是最無聊的投資方式，但同時也是最穩妥的一個方法。投資組合包括指數型基金（ETF），債券，以及現金，僅僅如此。
作者以各種基金為例，說明連最資深最有經驗的股票投資人，所賺得的升幅都未必比得上市場的升幅。作為一般大眾的我們，又要如何打敗市場呢？因此，以不急需使用的財富定期買進指數型基金，長線地投資（至少5-10年起跳），最後都會有可觀的回報。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;主動積極投資自己的人生&#34;&gt;主動積極投資自己的人生&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;本書花了不少篇幅在討論如何投資財富上。但著墨更多的，還是在如何投資在自己上面。即使僅以賺錢這一個目標出發，投資金錢也未必是唯一的途徑。增進自己，才是更好的捷徑。至於如何投資自己，作者也給出了幾個建議：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;開源節流 - 找到有興趣的副業，並學會如何儲蓄&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;學習 - 增值自己，以獲得更好的工作，又或者令自己有本錢要求更高的薪金&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;善用時間 - 善用時間做自己最擅長的東西，將大部分時間投資在高價值的事情上。減少為繁瑣卻無用的事情憂心，那便可以省下更多的時間享受生活。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;特別講一下儲蓄這一部分。如果想要達至所謂財富自由，儲蓄是不可獲缺的一件事。即使幸得橫財，不善加利用不停揮霍的話最後也只會窮困潦倒。書中提到，我們可以循序漸進，從1%開始。看似微不足道，但當習慣後逐步加到2%，3%，10%，長久積累後便是一筆不少的積蓄。雖然不是甚麼快速致富的方法，但卻是最基本人人可以做到的事情。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;結語&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;結語&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;相信大部分人對生活的都是爲了享受，而不是受苦。其實本書有一個貫徹始終的觀念，那就是&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;不要拖延由今天開始做起&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;不要拖延，由今天開始做起。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;無論是儲蓄，學習，規劃時間，甚至與珍惜的人相處，還是享受，一切如是。
希望大家在看完這篇閲讀筆記后，能有幾分得著，甚至對這本書產生興趣！感謝~&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
