<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hi! on James&#39; Blog</title>
    <link>https://hkwind.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hi! on James&#39; Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2008–2018, Steve Francia and the Hugo Authors; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hkwind.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Road to IELTS</title>
      <link>https://hkwind.github.io/post/ieltsroad2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hkwind.github.io/post/ieltsroad2022/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I&#39;m going to take IELTS in about one month. This blog is the record of how I try to improve in English, especially in writing and speaking.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;foreword&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreword&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi there! Don&#39;t know how you stumbled upon this blog. Honestly, this blog is just a place for me to record my progress in improving my writing and speaking skills. I&#39;ll mark some of the websites and Youtube channels that I find useful during my learning journey, but don&#39;t expect to learn much. I&#39;ll keep updating till I finally get my IELTS result, so stay tuned if you are interested!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-current-level&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My current level&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, I had my last IELTS exam. I would say that I got pretty lucky, as I got a 9 in reading and an 8 in listening, which saved me from my below par score in writing (6.0) and speaking (6.5), resulting in a total score of 7.5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 2 years, i.e. today, I&#39;ve registered for another IELTS exam. This time, my aim is to get at least 7.0 in all subjects and total score as 7.5. It is never an easy challenge, especially I&#39;ve got only one and a half month to start working on my English skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;things-ill-do&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things I&#39;ll do&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;reading--listening&#34;&gt;Reading &amp;amp; Listening&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For reading and listening, all I will do is some IELTS exercise that I rent from the library. As my time is precious, I believe that I should put my focus on getting better in writing and speaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;writing--speaking&#34;&gt;Writing &amp;amp; Speaking&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I&#39;ve identified some of my weakness in writing and speaking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Writing Tree&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;style&gt;
  
  .node {
    cursor: pointer;
  }

  .node circle {
    fill: #fff;
    stroke: steelblue;
    stroke-width: 3px;
  }

  .node text {
    font: 12px sans-serif;
  }

  .link {
    fill: none;
    stroke: #ccc;
    stroke-width: 2px;
  }
  
    &lt;/style&gt;

  &lt;/head&gt;

  &lt;body&gt;

&lt;!-- load the d3.js library --&gt; 
&lt;script src=&#34;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/d3/3.5.17/d3.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  
&lt;script&gt;

var treeData = [
  {
    &#34;name&#34;: &#34;Writing&#34;,
    &#34;parent&#34;: &#34;null&#34;,
    &#34;children&#34;: [
      {
        &#34;name&#34;: &#34;Grammar&#34;,
        &#34;parent&#34;: &#34;Writing&#34;,
        &#34;children&#34;: [
          {
            &#34;name&#34;: &#34;Youtube Channel: Ms. Charlotte&#34;,
            &#34;parent&#34;: &#34;Grammar&#34;
          },
        ]
      },
      {
        &#34;name&#34;: &#34;IELTS Writing Format&#34;
        &#34;parent&#34;: &#34;Writing&#34;
        &#34;children&#34;: [
          {
            &#34;name&#34;: &#34;Website: Ms. Liz&#34;,
            &#34;parent&#34;: &#34;IELTS Writing Format&#34;
          },
        ]
      }
      {
        &#34;name&#34;: &#34;Vocabulary&#34;
        &#34;parent&#34;: &#34;Writing&#34;
        &#34;children&#34;: [
          {
            &#34;name&#34;: &#34;Memorizing software: Anki&#34;,
            &#34;parent&#34;: &#34;Vocabulary&#34;
          },
        ]
      }
    ]
  }
];


// ************** Generate the tree diagram  *****************
var margin = {top: 20, right: 120, bottom: 20, left: 120},
  width = 960 - margin.right - margin.left,
  height = 500 - margin.top - margin.bottom;
  
var i = 0,
  duration = 750,
  root;

var tree = d3.layout.tree()
  .size([height, width]);

var diagonal = d3.svg.diagonal()
  .projection(function(d) { return [d.y, d.x]; });

var svg = d3.select(&#34;body&#34;).append(&#34;svg&#34;)
  .attr(&#34;width&#34;, width + margin.right + margin.left)
  .attr(&#34;height&#34;, height + margin.top + margin.bottom)
  .append(&#34;g&#34;)
  .attr(&#34;transform&#34;, &#34;translate(&#34; + margin.left + &#34;,&#34; + margin.top + &#34;)&#34;);

root = treeData[0];
root.x0 = height / 2;
root.y0 = 0;
  
update(root);

d3.select(self.frameElement).style(&#34;height&#34;, &#34;500px&#34;);

function update(source) {

  // Compute the new tree layout.
  var nodes = tree.nodes(root).reverse(),
    links = tree.links(nodes);

  // Normalize for fixed-depth.
  nodes.forEach(function(d) { d.y = d.depth * 180; });

  // Update the nodes…
  var node = svg.selectAll(&#34;g.node&#34;)
    .data(nodes, function(d) { return d.id || (d.id = ++i); });

  // Enter any new nodes at the parent&#39;s previous position.
  var nodeEnter = node.enter().append(&#34;g&#34;)
    .attr(&#34;class&#34;, &#34;node&#34;)
    .attr(&#34;transform&#34;, function(d) { return &#34;translate(&#34; + source.y0 + &#34;,&#34; + source.x0 + &#34;)&#34;; })
    .on(&#34;click&#34;, click);

  nodeEnter.append(&#34;circle&#34;)
    .attr(&#34;r&#34;, 1e-6)
    .style(&#34;fill&#34;, function(d) { return d._children ? &#34;lightsteelblue&#34; : &#34;#fff&#34;; });

  nodeEnter.append(&#34;text&#34;)
    .attr(&#34;x&#34;, function(d) { return d.children || d._children ? -13 : 13; })
    .attr(&#34;dy&#34;, &#34;.35em&#34;)
    .attr(&#34;text-anchor&#34;, function(d) { return d.children || d._children ? &#34;end&#34; : &#34;start&#34;; })
    .text(function(d) { return d.name; })
    .style(&#34;fill-opacity&#34;, 1e-6);

  // Transition nodes to their new position.
  var nodeUpdate = node.transition()
    .duration(duration)
    .attr(&#34;transform&#34;, function(d) { return &#34;translate(&#34; + d.y + &#34;,&#34; + d.x + &#34;)&#34;; });

  nodeUpdate.select(&#34;circle&#34;)
    .attr(&#34;r&#34;, 10)
    .style(&#34;fill&#34;, function(d) { return d._children ? &#34;lightsteelblue&#34; : &#34;#fff&#34;; });

  nodeUpdate.select(&#34;text&#34;)
    .style(&#34;fill-opacity&#34;, 1);

  // Transition exiting nodes to the parent&#39;s new position.
  var nodeExit = node.exit().transition()
    .duration(duration)
    .attr(&#34;transform&#34;, function(d) { return &#34;translate(&#34; + source.y + &#34;,&#34; + source.x + &#34;)&#34;; })
    .remove();

  nodeExit.select(&#34;circle&#34;)
    .attr(&#34;r&#34;, 1e-6);

  nodeExit.select(&#34;text&#34;)
    .style(&#34;fill-opacity&#34;, 1e-6);

  // Update the links…
  var link = svg.selectAll(&#34;path.link&#34;)
    .data(links, function(d) { return d.target.id; });

  // Enter any new links at the parent&#39;s previous position.
  link.enter().insert(&#34;path&#34;, &#34;g&#34;)
    .attr(&#34;class&#34;, &#34;link&#34;)
    .attr(&#34;d&#34;, function(d) {
    var o = {x: source.x0, y: source.y0};
    return diagonal({source: o, target: o});
    });

  // Transition links to their new position.
  link.transition()
    .duration(duration)
    .attr(&#34;d&#34;, diagonal);

  // Transition exiting nodes to the parent&#39;s new position.
  link.exit().transition()
    .duration(duration)
    .attr(&#34;d&#34;, function(d) {
    var o = {x: source.x, y: source.y};
    return diagonal({source: o, target: o});
    })
    .remove();

  // Stash the old positions for transition.
  nodes.forEach(function(d) {
  d.x0 = d.x;
  d.y0 = d.y;
  });
}

// Toggle children on click.
function click(d) {
  if (d.children) {
  d._children = d.children;
  d.children = null;
  } else {
  d.children = d._children;
  d._children = null;
  }
  update(d);
}

&lt;/script&gt;
  
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, my biggest weakness: &lt;strong&gt;grammar&lt;/strong&gt;. I feel like that I never really think throuoghly on why am I using certain tense, but just using it by will.
Also, my sentence structure is bad that I never write good sentences.
It&#39;s okay for daily conversation, but certainly bad for exams like IELTS.
Therefore, I need to find way to learn how to use tenses appropriately and write better structured sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I&#39;ll study through a Youtube channel&#39;s video: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/c/MsCharlotteAcademy&#34;&gt;Ms. Charlotte&lt;/a&gt;.
I&#39;ve gone through some of her videos, and I feel like that as a Hongkonger, its the first time I really listen to some good explaination in English grammar and sentence structure in Cantonese. (Sorry for any foreign viewer, if any (・∀・) )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another weakness for me is &lt;strong&gt;IELTS writing structure&lt;/strong&gt;. Last time, I had prepared nothing for the IELTS test, and therefore faced difficulties in writing articles that matched IELTS requirement. So therefore, I believe that pay more attention to the related things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One website that I find very useful is &lt;a href=&#34;https://ieltsliz.com/&#34;&gt;IELTS Liz&lt;/a&gt;.
Not only it gives a lot of advice on how to write an IELTS-format article, it also includes sample questions and answers that allow us to try writing. I believe that doing something is the best way to learn, so able to actually write something then have a model answer to reference on seems good for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My last weakness is &lt;strong&gt;vocabulary&lt;/strong&gt;, which I guess you should have noticed it when you are reading this and my other blog.
I find it hard to improve on, expecially when I usaully just use the first word that pops up in my brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IELTS Liz can help, but I need more than that to really memorize them and utilize the new words in my article and conversation.
What I can think of is to use Anki, a software that I&#39;ve mentioned before (&lt;a href=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/post/learning-how-to-learn/&#34;&gt;My Blog &#39;Learning how to learn&#39;&lt;/a&gt;)
Through this software, hopefully I can memorize more words and therefore use a variety of them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-plan&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My plan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, my aim is to at least write an article thrice a week, i.e. 1 article in around 2-3 days. Besides that, I&#39;ll listen to videos, drop notes and add new words in my Anki. I&#39;ll update this in next week, so lets see how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update on 21-3-2022: I&#39;ve already tried to study IELTS for 1 week. Writing article really helps to show how bad I&#39;m currently. One new discovery is that the ability to write similar sentences in different way must also be mastered , as a good article cannot have every sentence looks alike right? IELTS Liz also have videos about sentence structure, but I still have to practice more in order to use the skills in my article.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>超速學習 Part 1</title>
      <link>https://hkwind.github.io/post/ultralearning_part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hkwind.github.io/post/ultralearning_part1/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;會想要進步，但卻又不知道應該如何著手？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;歡迎來到《超速學習》的讀書會，希望超速學習此書可以作爲你的好夥伴，跟你一起走上學習之路。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/UltralearningCover.png&#34; width = &#34;200&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;前言&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;前言&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;學習是人生的必經之路，但卻不是人人都知道如何學習。你有時會覺得自己好像不知道如何才能牢固學會一項有用的才能嗎？會想要進步，但卻又不知道應該如何著手？歡迎來到《超速學習》的讀書會，希望《超速學習》此書可以作爲你的好夥伴，跟你一起走上學習之路。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在此書中，作者列出了九個學習的法則。當然，每一個都非常重要，經過思考後我應該也會將大部分列出，但會有所著重，以不會太過長氣的方式簡述各個要訣的關鍵以及個人親身嘗試的經歷，也因爲長度的原因，將會分爲兩篇閲讀筆記。第一篇講述如何能夠開始超速學習，第二篇則是關於應該如何學習。如果看完這兩篇筆記後對此書有興趣，可以到各大書局或圖書館尋寶~&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;在成為超速學習者之前&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;在成為超速學習者之前。。。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在講述這些法則之前，好像先應該說一下超速學習的作用。原作者在書中列出了許多曾經達成過的成就，但最為人所知的應該是他用僅僅一年就自修完成了一般學生需要四年才能完成的MIT資訊科技學位課程（MIT Challenge）。也有不少人曾經運用過裡面的技巧，完成了不同大小的目標；我也曾經運用過部分的技巧在學習當中，並獲得了不錯的成效。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;現在我們確定了超速學習的成效了，但可能你還是會有種種的疑慮，那就讓我們先來解答一些可能的問題：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;超速學習是什麼&#34;&gt;超速學習是什麼？&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;其實連作者自己也未能為超速學習下一個簡單易明的定義，不過我自己是把它當成一個應該如何學習的框架。它有一些指引，但我們不需要盲從，而是需要知道什麼時候採用什麼策略。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但超速學習有一個精神，便是要求使用者要執行一種 &lt;strong&gt;高強度的自主學習&lt;/strong&gt;。不停的練習和反覆磨練，而不是抱持著玩玩的精神，非常認真的針對每一個項目訂下學習計畫並確實執行，這才是超速學習的成效來源。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;超速學習會需要我投放所有的時間嗎&#34;&gt;超速學習會需要我投放所有的時間嗎？&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;答案是可以，但不是必須。你投放越多的時間，越專心在這一個項目上，當然成效會越好，就好像本書作者完成MIT Challenge一樣。但這並不代表假設我們只有課餘工餘時間，這些技巧便會一無是處。反而，這些技巧能夠幫助我們利用僅有的時間，發揮出100%的生產力。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;不知道上面的解答夠不夠讓你決定要了解更多關於超速學習的細節。無論如何，讓我們開始講述超速學習的第一個法則：後設學習（如何開始超速學習），可能你會發現更多《超速學習》的奧妙。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;一後設學習先畫一張學習地圖&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;一。後設學習──先畫一張學習地圖&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在小時候，我們上課時沒有想過究竟學會的知識實際上有什麽作用，只是根據課本、老師、父母的指引來學習。可能小孩還沒有足夠的能力去分辨什麽是我們需要的，但看到這篇筆記的你們，我相信你們都有能力去判斷什麽才是自己現在最需要的。因此，超速學習的第一個元素「後設學習」，便是要求大家先想好自己的目標，再由此反推出自己需要學習些什麽。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;WHY？&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在最初的一開始，不妨先讓我們去想一下我們的目標。學好一項外語？學會踩單車？而又是爲什麽我們想達成這項目標？目標又分為本質性與功能性。本質性代表你就是純粹想達到這項目標，例如學日語，拉小提琴之類，沒有什麼背後的原因。這種的話就不需要考慮太多，可以到下一步了，我們著重討論功能性的目標。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;功能性的目標，代表的是你背後是有一個原因去做的，例如我學習更多的coding技巧，去做種種的project（目標），是為了建立起自己的profolio，未來可以找到一份有關AI 的工作（背後原因）。但這時候，我們首先需要深思的是，究竟這項目標是不是真的可以為我們達成背後的目的，否則這一切都只是浪費時間。因此，在開始做之前，做一些相關的研究是必須的，例如先詢問一些在相關產業的人士，或是更簡單在網上先搜尋一下。當確定好目標是適合的以後，我們便可以開始想該做些什麼。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;what&#34;&gt;WHAT？&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在我們寫下我們該做些什麼時，讓我們先在腦中把這項技能拆解，或者也是在網上調查一下。以小提琴為例，有什麼是需要學習的呢？首先，拉小提琴的姿勢以及拉弓的方式。其次，手按弦的位置以及技巧。最後，閱讀樂譜的能力。當然可能會有更多的需要，但目前我的腦海中就只浮現了這幾項。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;之後，我們可以把這些想到要學習的東西分類。
&lt;br&gt;第一類是需要理解的東西，被稱為&lt;strong&gt;概念（Concepts）&lt;/strong&gt;，例如樂譜上各種符號的含義。
&lt;br&gt;第二類是只需要記住的東西，不需要去多加理解的，被稱為&lt;strong&gt;事實（Facts）&lt;/strong&gt;，例如手按弦的位置（只需要知道按哪幾個位置便會出什麼音）。
&lt;br&gt;第三類是需要反覆練習的東西，被稱為&lt;strong&gt;程序（Procedures）&lt;/strong&gt;，例如拉小提琴的姿勢，拉弓的方式，按弦的方式，等等等等。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;分離出這些不同類型的知識，是因為它們需要使用不同的方式去學習。當所有技能都至少粗通後，並可以融會貫通，並統整為：我開始學會拉小提琴了！因此在最後，我們需要解答的問題便是該如何做到上述的一切。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;how&#34;&gt;HOW？&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我們需要開始尋找有什麼資料和教材是我們所需要的。作者提供了一個方法，叫做&lt;em&gt;標竿學習法&lt;/em&gt;。簡單而言，便是去找一下學校裡用來教導那個科目的課程，教科書，甚至是在網上搜尋。
我們也可以查詢一下專家或相關人士的意見，找到有效且直接的方法去開始學習。
例如上面我需要理解樂譜上各種符號的含義，一本相關的教科書便有助我去找到各種我需要認識的樂譜符號。對於拉弓的方式，我可能會在YouTube 搜尋拉小提琴的影片，並找一些容易學習的去嘗試模仿。當然，找一個老師也是不錯的方法，但這並不是必須的，重點是我們需要自己主動去不停訓練，才能獲得2的效果。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;計劃過後&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;計劃過後。。。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;以「後設學習」去訂立計劃，我覺得是非常重要的一件事。做好了計畫以後，我們才可以循序漸進的開始我們學習的旅程，但計畫過後沒有實作也是白費。在下一篇筆記，將會講述八項關於我們應該如何學習的法則。讓我們在下一篇筆記再會！&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s build a blog with GitHub and Hugo - Part 1 - GitHub Settings</title>
      <link>https://hkwind.github.io/post/howtobuildablog_part1_github/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hkwind.github.io/post/howtobuildablog_part1_github/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Wanna blog? Follow the instruction and build yourself a blog in a day or two!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!---thumbnail = &#34;&#34;--&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
#	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/MillionareInYou_CoverPic.jpg&#34; width = &#34;200&#34;/&gt;
# &lt;/p&gt;--&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: &lt;br /&gt; I’m not an expert in building a blog and I do not know every feature in Github &amp;amp; Hugo. &lt;br /&gt;
However, we are on the same learning journey. I would love to share what I have learnt. &lt;br /&gt;
Therefore, if you have some problems, feel free to raise them. Then, we can discuss it here and everyone can learn something from it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;foreword&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreword&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome! I suppose you want to start blogging. For whatever purpose, that does not matter.
What matters is that you do want to build your own blog, and you stumble upon this article.
In this series of blog articles, I’ll show you how to create your own website and blog, and more importantly how to maintain it. Let&#39;s get started!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub is a place where developers can upload, manage and control versions of their code. In technical terms, it is called a repository.
What’s unique about Github is that it can be used as a hosting service provider.
Therefore, after we upload our code and do some settings changes in GitHub, it will automatically help us build a website! How convenient!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;create-github-account&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create GitHub Account&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step is to create a GitHub account. First, go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/&#34;&gt;https://github.com/&lt;/a&gt; and start the signup procedure. GitHub gives clear instructions, so you can simply follow them. One thing to notice: Be careful about your username, as it should be shown in your website URL later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_CreateUser.png&#34; width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_SelectFeature.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As before mentioned, we will be going with the costless option i.e. the free plan.
The GitHub free plan has already got all the functionalities we need.
If you are feeling good later and wants to upgrade, it&#39;s up to you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_Free_Plan.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;create-project-repository&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create Project Repository&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After filling in all required information and finishing all necessary verifications, you should be led to the dashboard page.
This is the so-called front page, and you can access all of your projects here.
Click the &amp;quot;New&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Create repository&amp;quot; button on the left panel to start building your account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_CreateRepository.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For repository name, it should be &amp;quot;yourusername&amp;quot;.github.io.
For example, as my username is &amp;quot;testinguser0122&amp;quot;, my repository name should be ‘testinguser0122.github.io‘.
This is also the URL people use to access your blog.
Beware that the repository should be public as GitHub web hosting services are only free for public repositories.
As for the below option, we should add a readme file (for introduction purposes) and add a license (GNU General Public License v3.0).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_CreateRepositoryFillData.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all settings have been set, we can click “Create” and the repository is ready!
As you can see, our repository only have two files: A README file and the LICENSE file.
We should add more files to it, but for now we can leave it as be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_RepositoryFrontPage.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;create-our-own-website&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create our own Website&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After setting up the repository, its time to build our own website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to settings page which the button should be around the top right corner of the project page.
In settings, go to the Pages and select Docs branch as the source for the repository. Click “Save” and the confirmation message &amp;quot;Your website is published&amp;quot; is shown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_PageSettings.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can then see that the page is published and the website can be accessed now! Your website should almost look identical just like mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Github_Webpage.png&#34;width = &#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ending&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ending&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are all set! Our website is built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well it looks blank and we have not yet put our content in.
&lt;br&gt;But don&#39;t worry, in the next blog, I will introduce you how to start making your blog. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning how to learn - A Cousera course Introduction</title>
      <link>https://hkwind.github.io/post/learning-how-to-learn/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hkwind.github.io/post/learning-how-to-learn/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;“Learning how to learn” is one of the most popular courses on Coursera. Check out this summary blog article and later if you are interested, go try out the completely free course!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/Learning How to Learn.png&#34; width = &#34;500&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;foreword&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreword&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome! Great to see you here!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Learning how to learn&amp;quot; is a 4-week course introducing different topics about effective learning each week.
&lt;br&gt;(Course link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&#34;&gt;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I will not go through everything about the course, as I believe you should attend it to understand how to learn effectively.
Therefore, I will only introduce the inspiring concepts and ideas from this course that I have applied in studying other topics.
Hope these techniques can help you in your learning journey as well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tackling-procrastination拖延how-to-start-learning&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tackling Procrastination（拖延）(How to start learning)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Procrastination is my biggest enemy. I must admit that I tend to avoid doing tedious work and move on to an activity that brings me pleasure. However, I often regret spending meaningless hours doing nothing, which leads to no actual accomplishments. Worse, the guilt may lead to a vicious circle, forcing me to do more leisure activities to escape from these negative feelings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course has mentioned several ideas to tackle procrastination. Some of them work for me effectively. Before mentioning them, I must point out that &lt;strong&gt;using willpower to defeat the idea of delaying&lt;/strong&gt; is not a good measure. Special shoutout to Pomodoro. It&#39;s a practical supporting tool and mindset that enhances study effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;planning&#34;&gt;Planning&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, make a plan. In the course, the instructor suggests everyone should maintain a planner journal and plan their next day before bed. By doing so, we remind ourselves of close deadlines and avoid rushing through everything (thus better products!). Also, it is suggested to plan the &lt;em&gt;most crucial and disliked task&lt;/em&gt; as the first task in the morning. We should be rested and back in the groove when we wake up. Therefore, we can use our 100% energy to focus on the task. After accomplishing it, we will have a sense of accomplishment throughout the day, leading to extra motivation towards the remaining hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally use a goal tracker to monitor my deadlines. Feel free to check my template out and use it to your own benefit.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1p54_NT58cR-NeDzRlMl5Ar9J3nxv2sBLot3eB8j6STw/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1p54_NT58cR-NeDzRlMl5Ar9J3nxv2sBLot3eB8j6STw/edit?usp=sharing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;focus-on-the-process&#34;&gt;Focus on the Process&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is to focus on the process rather than the product. Products can be scary, for example, a 5000-word essay, a project that weighs 50% of your total grade, or even blog articles that require updating weekly. We may want to escape from these intimidating aims, resulting in procrastination. Instead, focus on the process: &amp;quot;Writing for an hour&amp;quot;. Does not seem that scary now. As long as we are productive and working on the right path, the outcome matters but is not the sole focus anymore. We may be surprised at how productive we can be by several hours!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;remove-procrastination-cues&#34;&gt;Remove Procrastination Cues&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third is to put yourself in surroundings with few procrastination cues. Most of us are weak and easily attracted to many things: mobile phones, TV, computers, people… As soon as these things catch our attention, we lose focus on our current task or even stop doing it. To avoid it from happening, find a place with the least attractions, for example, a study room. Especially for your phones, place them somewhere you cannot see them. &lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can do whatever you want with your phone during rest periods, but do your best to focus on tasks when working.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-learn-better&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Learn Better&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course introduces several concepts to learn effectively. What I found the most noteworthy is the idea of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;Illusion of Competence&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  It means that our actions lead to a false sense that we have already understood the concepts. For example, we may just glance through the answer to a question and feel like we have a grasp of the way to answer similar questions. Another common loophole is that we highlight and underline the key concepts and all of a sudden fully understand what it means. We may even just practice on the easy stuff and truly believe that we have mastered the skill! These are just illusions, which will break when we face real difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the course has introduced concepts and techniques that help us to 1. memorize and 2. become proficient in different fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;spaced-repetition-technique&#34;&gt;Spaced Repetition Technique&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, we think we have memorized something, but after a few hours or days, we forget them. It is because we only remember them in our working memory, but not in long-term memory. To access long term memory and really remember something, the “Spaced Repetition Technique” is the way to go. Instead of forcing yourself to learn something in an hour and never revise it again, try to do shorter intervals but in several days. By recalling after some time, it helps to form and strengthen our long term memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;metaphor-and-analogy&#34;&gt;Metaphor and Analogy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do have to understand things before we can memorize them. Also, memorizing a cumbersome chunk of concepts without paraphrasing is hard. We can try using Metaphor and Analogy to paraphrase ideas into things that are easier to remember. By drawing an imaginary picture in our head, we can access our visual memory system. It gives us an extra cue to remember stuff and effectively stores them in our long-term memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;diffuse-mode&#34;&gt;Diffuse Mode&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course mentioned techniques on how to tackle problems as well. Solving problems show our competence to utilize the knowledge in our brain and ensure that we have fully understood the concepts. The instructor suggests that &amp;quot;Diffuse mode&amp;quot; is crucial when conquering problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our brains have a focused mode and a diffuse mode. The focused mode works when we are concentrating on tasks, while the diffuse mode works when we are not. Studies show that we are more creative and good at solving challenging questions when in diffuse mode. Therefore, next time you are struggling with a question or task, try to do easier questions or be relaxed to activate diffuse mode!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;suggested-tools&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suggested tools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;pomodoro&#34;&gt;Pomodoro&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pomodoro is actually a very well known technique. I knew about it even before attending the course. However, I have seen many failed cases online, claiming that Pomodoro has no help in their study or work. I believe that how to utilize Pomodoro is more important than the technique itself. A book review related to Pomodoro (in Chinese only) will be posted in the coming weeks. Stay tuned if you want to know more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pomodoro has two significant rules to follow in my opinion. The first is allowing resting periods between working sections. As most of you may know, Pomodoro consists of a cycle of working sections that lasts for around 25-30 mins then followed by a 5-10 mins rest. After 4 or more working sections, you can rest for a longer period (10-30 min). Most people understand this logic but neglect the importance of the rest period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/PomodoroTechnique.png&#34; width = &#34;500&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can only be fully focused for a period of time, then our productivity will go lower and lower as time passes. By resting (i.e. not doing work-related stuff and relaxing), first we can recharge our energy and be better prepared in the next working section. What&#39;s more, it enables diffuse mode (mentioned above) thus it helps us to solve complicated problems as well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is to be focused on one and only one task when in one working section. If you have ideas and thoughts related to other topics during working, use a notebook to mark them down. It is to ensure that we can dedicate most of our attention and energy to our work in front of us. Email checking, Instagram checking, booking a concert ticket... Sure, but do it in resting periods or next Pomodoro period. Focus on one task at a time shows better results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ending&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ending&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course has also mentioned the Anki flashcard system, which is a tool for memorizing things. I will try it in my later study and may add an additional paragraph introducing it later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, hope you enjoyed reading this article and learn a thing or two. Feel free to check out my other blog post and also the course!
Course link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&#34;&gt;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s build a blog with GitHub and Hugo - Introduction</title>
      <link>https://hkwind.github.io/post/howtobuildablog_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hkwind.github.io/post/howtobuildablog_intro/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Wanna blog? Follow the instruction and build yourself a blog in a day or two!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!---thumbnail = &#34;&#34;--&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
#	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/MillionareInYou_CoverPic.jpg&#34; width = &#34;200&#34;/&gt;
# &lt;/p&gt;--&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: &lt;br /&gt; I’m not an expert in building a blog and I do not know every feature in Github &amp;amp; Hugo. &lt;br /&gt;
However, we are on the same learning journey. I would love to share what I have learnt. &lt;br /&gt;
Therefore, if you have some problems, feel free to raise them. Then, we can discuss it here and everyone can learn something from it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;foreword&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreword&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome! I suppose you want to start blogging. For whatever purpose, that does not matter.
What matters is that you do want to build your own blog, and you stumble upon this article.
In this series of blog articles, I’ll show you how to create your own website and blog, and more importantly how to maintain it. Let&#39;s get started!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this series, as the header says, we are using Github and Hugo to build the blog.
I’ve tried several ways to construct my blog, and eventually, I’m satisfied with this outcome.
That’s why at the start of this introduction article, I’m going to show you why I would build my blog with Github and Hugo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;advantages-of-using-github--hugo-to-build-a-blog&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantages of using GitHub &amp;amp; Hugo to build a blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;free-price&#34;&gt;Free Price&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, it is free. TOTALLY FREE. Not even a single penny was spent when building this blog. All you need is a PC to save the files, an internet connection so you can connect with the GitHub server, and an email (Google Mail is fine) account to create a Github account. Therefore, even if you are uncertain about whether you will continue blogging, your desire to try blogging won’t be deterred by the monthly / yearly subscription fee of those blog hosting sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;low-setup-difficulty&#34;&gt;Low Setup Difficulty&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, it is easy to set up. Of course, Medium and other blog hosting websites do not require setup at all, but free things come with a cost. However, the setup process of Github and Hugo are much less complicated than other free options, which makes this combination a better choice than the others. Usually, you can finish setup and post your first blog within the first few days if you have followed the steps in this blog carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;no-requirement-on-programming-knowledge&#34;&gt;No requirement on programming knowledge&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, you can build your own blog without any prerequisite programming knowledge. Or let me paraphrase it, you do not need any programming knowledge because I have done most of the programming work for you. What you need to do is follow the steps. However, you still have to know something about coding for uploading blogs (very easy) and customizing the blog (a bit harder), which will be discussed in later sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ending&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ending&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that has been said, I’m sure you understand what’s the benefit of going for the Github + Hugo approach. If you’re confident that you want to try it out, let&#39;s continue on our next blog: Create a GitHub account and domain.&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>賺錢，也賺幸福</title>
      <link>https://hkwind.github.io/post/millionareinyou_20220101/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hkwind.github.io/post/millionareinyou_20220101/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;你有沒有想過，自己賺錢的目的是爲了甚麽？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;歡迎來到《賺錢，也賺幸福》的讀書會，讓我們一起來探討應該如何策劃自己的人生。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&#34;https://hkwind.github.io/images/MillionareInYou_CoverPic.jpg&#34; width = &#34;200&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Millionaire In You: Ten Things You Need To Do Now To Have Money And Time To Enjoy It&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;主動積極投資自己的人生，被動投資你的金錢
(麥可．勒巴夫 Michael LeBoeuf)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;前言&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;前言&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;你有沒有想過，自己工作的目的是爲了甚麽？每天辛勤工作，忙得連輕鬆的時間都欠奉，只爲了讓年老體衰時能過著不算太差的生活？除了工作，你又有沒有想過自己的人生還有著什麽目標？歡迎來到《賺錢，也賺幸福》的讀書會，讓我們一起來探討應該如何策劃自己的人生。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在此書内，作者一共列出了四大見解，十大選擇以及四大要務，個人覺得此書的每一個章節都有其獨特的見解，實在值得一看再看。但畢竟這是我個人的閲讀筆記，因此我並不會將其中的内容全部寫出，而是會對抽取其中的内容做一些整合以及加入一些個人心得。如果閱讀完這篇筆記后想瞭解更多内容，歡迎到各大書局或圖書館尋寶~&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;一規劃人生分配時間&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;一。規劃人生，分配時間&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;夢想&#34;&gt;夢想&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;你有想過未來一年，十年，二十年，甚至退休的時候，你希望自己正活著一個怎樣的人生嗎？如果沒有的話，不如現在就來想一下對於將來的盼望和目標？你可能會覺得夢想對你來説有一點不切實際。亦有可能，你會覺得夢想是不必要的，只需要專注於目前的工作就可以了。但是，「做人如果無夢想，同條鹹魚有咩分別呀？」夢想作爲我們的原動力，能夠推動我們成爲更好的自己。我們也需要夢想，引領我們走上一條我們享受的人生路。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果上面的問題對你來説有一點空泛，我們可以用書中的兩個問題作出發點：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;希望N年后的人生有些甚麽？&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;怎樣知道自己已經擁有了想要的東西？&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;第一個問題的答案當然可能會有非常多：很多很多錢，一個安身之所，甚至可以是開心這種比較虛無的概念（夢想應該是多方面的，包括個人成長，家庭及朋友，健康，等等），因此我們以第二個問題來令虛無的概念具體化，如「我擁有一百萬就等於很多很多錢」 / 「我一天能有三個小時的時間打機就等於開心」。一個具體化的夢想，有助我們去走下一步：訂立目標。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;目標&#34;&gt;目標&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;有了一個概念，或者説是對於未來的幻想之後，當然不可以止步於此。你需要做的，是將你的夢想化爲對於未來的規劃，並定下各種的目標，然後確實實行。
書中認爲目標應該具備可信性（是可以做到的事情），振奮性（達成時會令自己雀躍而非沮喪），明確性（一個可以量化的成果）以及完成期限（Deadline!!!)，例如「我在三年後銀行存款要有五十萬」。當你根據你的夢想訂立了不同的目標后，就將他們根據重要性排序，然後開始定出行動計劃。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;行動計劃&#34;&gt;行動計劃&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每一個目標都應該有它們各自的行動計劃，畢竟沒有行動的目標只是空想。跟目標一樣，行動計劃也是要具備另外，書中有一個概念叫做「即知即行」，意思是知道怎樣做就要開始去做。要知道每當我們給自己藉口拖延一天，我們離達成目標的日子就會遠一天。當然，我們也需要適當的休息，而且不斷的工作也只會令效率降低。因此，我們需要做的是計劃好后便坐言起行，一直追蹤自己的進度，並在適當的時候給予自己獎勵。
最後，要知道計劃一定不會完美無缺，意外終會發生，阻礙你順利完成計劃。在計劃中預留一些彈性的時間，可以令自己不會因爲意外而執行不了計劃，導致灰心喪志自暴自棄。
而且，有目標並堅定前進的人總會比懶散的人更容易獲得成功，宇宙會祝福你的~&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;二投資自己投資人生&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;二。投資自己，投資人生&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;其實跟規劃人生有一點類似，但這一部分會更加著重於投資。今年美國股市暢旺，加上加密貨幣、NFT 等新型的投資物品開始出現，相信每一個人都會想有開始投資的慾望或者已經開始進入了投資這個領域。不過呢，本書所宣導的投資方式卻與這些無緣。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;被動投資你的金錢&#34;&gt;被動投資你的金錢&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;這本書所宣導的投資方式，可以說是最無聊的投資方式，但同時也是最穩妥的一個方法。投資組合包括指數型基金（ETF），債券，以及現金，僅僅如此。
作者以各種基金為例，說明連最資深最有經驗的股票投資人，所賺得的升幅都未必比得上市場的升幅。作為一般大眾的我們，又要如何打敗市場呢？因此，以不急需使用的財富定期買進指數型基金，長線地投資（至少5-10年起跳），最後都會有可觀的回報。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;主動積極投資自己的人生&#34;&gt;主動積極投資自己的人生&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;本書花了不少篇幅在討論如何投資財富上。但著墨更多的，還是在如何投資在自己上面。即使僅以賺錢這一個目標出發，投資金錢也未必是唯一的途徑。增進自己，才是更好的捷徑。至於如何投資自己，作者也給出了幾個建議：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;開源節流 - 找到有興趣的副業，並學會如何儲蓄&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;學習 - 增值自己，以獲得更好的工作，又或者令自己有本錢要求更高的薪金&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;善用時間 - 善用時間做自己最擅長的東西，將大部分時間投資在高價值的事情上。減少為繁瑣卻無用的事情憂心，那便可以省下更多的時間享受生活。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;特別講一下儲蓄這一部分。如果想要達至所謂財富自由，儲蓄是不可獲缺的一件事。即使幸得橫財，不善加利用不停揮霍的話最後也只會窮困潦倒。書中提到，我們可以循序漸進，從1%開始。看似微不足道，但當習慣後逐步加到2%，3%，10%，長久積累後便是一筆不少的積蓄。雖然不是甚麼快速致富的方法，但卻是最基本人人可以做到的事情。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;結語&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;結語&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;相信大部分人對生活的都是爲了享受，而不是受苦。其實本書有一個貫徹始終的觀念，那就是&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;不要拖延由今天開始做起&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;不要拖延，由今天開始做起。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;無論是儲蓄，學習，規劃時間，甚至與珍惜的人相處，還是享受，一切如是。
希望大家在看完這篇閲讀筆記后，能有幾分得著，甚至對這本書產生興趣！感謝~&lt;/p&gt;
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
